A Guide to the Henkel Family Papers, 1801-2008: SC 0253
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Henkel Family Papers,
Special Collections, James Madison University
Henkel Family
SC 0253
1.08 cubic feet; 3 boxes
The Henkel Family Papers, 1801-2008, document the influential Henkel family of Rockingham and Shenandoah counties in Virginia's Shenandoah Valley. The collection, primarily documenting the Siram and Margaret Koiner Henkel line of the family, is comprised of correspondence, personal and financial papers, and genealogical research materials.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Acquired from Jeffrey S. Evans & Associates' November 10, 2017 Americana & Fine Antiques Auction, Featuring Virginia and the South auction.
Provenance
Material was property of a Henkel family descendant, presumably Mildred Renalds Wittig, great-granddaughter of Siram and Margaret Koiner Henkel.
Bio/Historical Note
Several complete and thorough genealogies have been written about the Henkel family and their contributions as doctors, printers, entrepreneurs, millers, and religious leaders. As such, this biographical note does not serve as an exhaustive rehashing of previous scholarship. Researchers are encouraged to review published secondary sources for additional information on the Henkel family.
The Henkel Family of Virginia's Shenandoah Valley descends from Rev. Paul Henkel (1754-1825) and Elizabeth Henkel (d. 1843). Siram Peter Henkel, who along with his immediate family is primarily documented in this collection, was the fifth child of Dr. Solomon Henkel (1777-1847) and Rebecca Miller Henkel (1780-1854) and grandson of Rev. Paul Henkel.
Siram was born March 16, 1809 in New Market, Virginia. In an attempt to follow in his father's footsteps, Siram attended, but did not complete, medical school at the University of Pennsylvania. He married Margaret Koiner (variously spelled Coiner) Henkel (1820-1899) of Augusta County, Virginia on June 30, 1835. The couple settled at "The Plains" – located between New Market and Timberville – in September 1835 and their thirteen children, many of whom are also documented in this collection, were born and raised there. Siram farmed various crops and also operated a store and mill at The Plains. The Plains Mill was erected between 1847 and 1849 under the direction of Siram and his father Solomon, prior to his death in August 1847.
During the American Civil War, two of Siram and Margeret's sons served for the Confederacy. Lewis Philip (1837-1904) served in the Ordance Department of the Confederate Army. Around 1863, Lewis became a member of Co. H (Valley Rangers) of the 10th Virginia Cavalry. Luther Melanchton (1841-1919) was also a member of the Confederate Army and wrote home to his father from various camps. Lewis and Luther's brother Samuel Augustus (1840-1885) was exempt from military duty due to medical reasons. He became epileptic after sustaining injuries from run-away horses in 1855.
In 1878, one year prior to Siram's death, he sketched the plans for a new house at Plains Mill. The house was built in 1882 and served as the residence for Siram's widow, Margaret, until her death in 1899. The aforementioned sketch and photographs of the completed house are found in this collection.
Scope and Content
The Henkel Family Papers, 1801-2008, document the influential Henkel family of Shenandoah and Rockingham counties in Virginia's Shenandoah Valley. The collection, chiefly documenting the Siram and Margaret Koiner Henkel line of the family, is comprised primarily of correspondence written to Siram P. Henkel and includes letters from his sons Lewis and Luther during their service in the American Civil War. The collection also includes personal and financial papers of various Henkel family members including Siram's children and genealogical research materials, much of which was used to inform Mildred Renalds Wittig's Henkel – Renalds Connection: with Ancestral Scripts and Collections (2014).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series. All series are arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1827-1913
Series 2: Personal Papers, 1801-1881
Series 3: Financial Files, 1832-1894
Series 4: Genealogy and Research Files, 1890-2008
Related Material
The following list includes related Henkel family manuscript collections.
Henkel Family Papers, 1783-1916, SC 0099, Special Collections, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.
Henkel Family Papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Henkel family records, 1838-1903. Business records collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond.
Henkel-Miller Family Papers, 1793-1910, #14434, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.
Henkel Plain Mills Store Daybook, 1835-1849, Special Collections Research Center, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Multiple collections under the accession number 8653, Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library.
Many of the documents in this collection are copied and transcribed in Mildred Renalds Wittig's Henkel – Renalds Connection (2014).
Separated Material
Several issues of serials including the Lutheran Church Visitor and the Southern Churchman have been removed from the collection and cataloged as part of Special Collections' rare book collection. Additionally, the facsimile publication of the Day Book for Solomon Henkel at the Plains Mills, Rockingham County, Virginia (2013) and Mildred Renalds Wittig's Henkel – Renalds Connection: with Ancestral Scripts and Collections (2nd ed., 2014) were removed from the collection and cataloged separately.
Bibliography
United States Department of the Interior, National Park Service. Plains Mill, VDHR File No. 082-5403, National Register of Historic Places Registration Form. 2014.
Wittig, Mildred Renalds. Henkel – Renalds Connection: with Ancestral Scripts and Collections. Harrisonburg, Va.: Custom Printing, 2014.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Henkel, Siram Peter, 1809-1879; Henkel family -- Correspondence; Slavery -- Virginia -- 19th century; Sawmills -- Virginia; New Market (Va.) -- History; Rockingham County (Va.) -- History; Rockingham County (Va.) -- Genealogy; Rockingham County (Va.) -- Social life and customs; Shenandoah County (Va.) -- History; Shenandoah County (Va.) -- Social life and customs; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- Genealogy; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- Social life and customs; Virginia -- History; Virginia -- History, Local; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Genre and Form Terms:
Letters (correspondence); Songbooks; Copybooks; Personal papers; Financial Records; Promissory notes; Receipts (financial records); Daybooks; Account books; Genealogies (histories); Research notes; Photographs; Postcards
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1827-1913
  Scope and Content
  Series 1: Correspondence, 1827-1913, chiefly contains letters written to Siram P. Henkel with correspondents including members of the Koiner/Coiner family of Augusta County, the Miller family of Winchester, and the Rupert family of Augusta County. The correspondents report on family and community news, marriages, health and illnesses, deaths, weather, harvest and planting updates, crop yields, and include fellow merchants requesting advice on the market of certain goods and numerous requests for Dr. Henkel's pills. Of particular interest are the letters written to Siram by his sons Lewis and Luther while serving in the American Civil War. The sons, and Luther in particular, write about camp life and general updates related to the war. In a December 21, 1861 letter to his father, Lewis P. Henkel writes from Winchester and mentions General Stonewall Jackson. He also refers to General Gilbert S. Meem as "Genl. Drunk."
  This series also contains correspondence to/from other Henkel family members including Dr. Solomon Henkel, Samuel G. Henkel, Solomon D. Henkel, Maggie Henkel Renalds, Lillian Henkel, and Margaret Koiner Henkel.
  The documentary record confirms that Margaret Koiner Henkel's family were enslavers and given the date of much of the correspondence, a portion relates to slavery and enslaved persons. Delia Koiner Overholt wrote to her sister Margaret Henkel on May 28, 1847 relaying the news of their grandfather's death. She goes on to write that "eleven or twelve blacks are to be sold and a great deal of property." In a January 24, 1857 letter to Siram Henkel, Delia Koiner Overholt writes again to describe in detail describes the sale of enslaved persons from her grandfather's estate. A similarly noteworthy letter, dated August 13, 1835, was penned by Siram Henkel to his wife Margaret in which he describes a large "drove" of enslaved persons that passed through the Valley. He describes the scene as follows: "There were eighty-four chained together to one long chain; there were also a great many women and children that were also in company; the whole number of men, women & children was two hundred and forty."
  All correspondence addressed to Dr. Solomon Henkel and/or Solomon Henkel P.M. is filed with Solomon Henkel (1777-1847), who was a practicing physician and served as Shenandoah County's first postmaster. A concerted effort was made on behalf of the archivist to not confuse his papers with those of his son Solomon David Henkel (1815-1872).
  Much of the correspondence includes envelopes or address leaves. The correspondence is arranged primarily by recipient, but in cases where the recipient is unknown (e.g. non-specific salutations and greetings or lack of return address), the correspondence is filed with miscellaneous correspondence. Some of the letters have non-original annotations on the address leaves relating to content or the correspondents.
  - Miscellaneous Henkel family correspondence, 1827-1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Margaret Koiner Henkel correspondence, 1835, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dr. Solomon Henkel correspondence, 1836-1846 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Margaret Koiner Henkel correspondence, 1840-1849 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1845-1846 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Solomon D. Henkel correspondence, 1845-1859 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Margaret Koiner Henkel correspondence, 1856-1896 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Heleah Margaret "Maggie" Henkel Renalds correspondence, 1883-1896 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Siram Henkel correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Series 2: Personal Papers, 1801-1881
  Series 2: Personal Papers, 1801-1881, includes miscellaneous papers from the immediate family of Siram Henkel. School papers and writing assignements from Siram and Margaret Henkel's children, Lewis, Samuel, Julia, Martin, and Maggie are included. The documents include a January 17, 1881 essay on politeness written by Maggie Henkel.
  The series also includes a manuscript music book penned by Siram's mother, Rebecca Miller Henkel, a grammar copybook belonging to Siram's brother Slyvanus Henkel, and Siram's 1878 plans for his family's new home place at Plains Mill.
  - Rebecca Miller Henkel manuscript music/songbook, 1801 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sylvanus Henkel grammar copybook, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lewis Henkel school papers, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Samuel A. Henkel school papers, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Henkel papers, 1856-1891, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Julia Henkel school papers, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Martin M. Henkel and Julia A. Henkel copybook, 1873-1874 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Siram Henkel sketch of Plains Mill house, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Heleah Margaret "Maggie" Henkel Renalds school papers, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series 3: Financial Files, 1832-1959
  Series 3: Financial Files, 1832-1894, contains receipts, ledger pages, and promissory notes. Included in Siram Henkel's financial papers is a form of the estimate and assessment of agricultural products to be taxed by the government of the Confederate States. Of particular interest is Paul P. Henkel's 1844-1872 daybook entitled "Sawmill Book No. 3" documenting the sawmill owned by Solomon Henkel. The daybook records prices for sawing and details sawing activities. Elizabeth Garber Renalds' account book and journal documents egg business and other farming and day-to-day activities while the family was living at the Lincoln Homestead on Linville Creek south of Broadway.
  - Miscellaneous Henkel family financial papers, 1832-1873, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Paul P. Henkel daybook/sawmill book no. 3, 1844-1872 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Siram Henkel financial papers, 1845-1884, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Solomon D. Henkel financial papers, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Dr. Solomon Henkel financial papers, 1847-1848 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Samuel A. Henkel financial papers, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Heleah Margaret "Maggie" Henkel Renalds financial papers, 1885-1890 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Heleah Margaret "Maggie" Henkel Renalds account book, 1893-1894 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Elizabeth Garber Renalds account book/journal, 1932-1959 (Box OV 1)
- Series 4: Genealogy and Research Files, 1890-2008
  Series 4: Genealogy and Research Files, 1890-2008, is comprised of research material, much of which was used to inform Mildred Renalds Wittig's Henkel – Renalds Connection: with Ancestral Scripts and Collections (2014). Documents include family trees, facsimiles of correspondence and manuscript material not otherwise found in this collection, photographs of Henkel family members and properties including Plains Mill and the Plains School, newspaper clippings, Henkel family reunion materials, and blank postcards. An oversize reproduction of a blank family register printed by Ambrose Henkel & Comp. is included.
  - Photographs, 1890-2007 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - General genealogy and research files, 1891-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 19, Box OV 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1953-2003, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Rev. Anthony Jacob Henkel Family National Association and reunions, 1972-2008 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence and manuscript facsimiles, undated (1822-1910) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Postcard, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)